<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Paul's last farewel, or A sermon, preached at the funerall of that godly and learned minister of Jesus Christ, Mr. Thomas Blake. By Anthony Burgesse, pastor of the church at Sutton-Coldfield in Warwickshire. With a funeral oration made at Mr. Blakes death by Samuel Shaw, then schoolmaster of the Free-School at Tamworth.</title>
            <author>Burgess, Anthony, d. 1664.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1658</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 47 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A77845</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B5652</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E937_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R207730</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99866766</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99866766</idno>
            <idno type="VID">119052</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A77845)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 119052)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 140:E937[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Paul's last farewel, or A sermon, preached at the funerall of that godly and learned minister of Jesus Christ, Mr. Thomas Blake. By Anthony Burgesse, pastor of the church at Sutton-Coldfield in Warwickshire. With a funeral oration made at Mr. Blakes death by Samuel Shaw, then schoolmaster of the Free-School at Tamworth.</title>
                  <author>Burgess, Anthony, d. 1664.</author>
                  <author>Shaw, Samuel, 1635-1696.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 24, [4] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Abel Roper, at the Sun against S. Dunstans Church in Fleet-street,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1658.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "marsh. 25".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Blake, Thomas, 1597?-1657.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons, English --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:119052:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Paul's laſt Farewel, <hi>OR A</hi> SERMON, PREACHED At the Funerall of that Godly and Learned Miniſter of JESUS CHRIST, <hi>M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi>
               </hi> THOMAS BLAKE.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Anthony Burgeſſe,</hi> Paſtor of the Church at <hi>Sutton-Coldfield</hi> in <hi>Warwickſhire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>With a Funeral <hi>ORATION</hi> made at Mr. <hi>Blakes</hi> death by <hi>Samuel Shaw,</hi> then Schoolmaſter of the Free-School at <hi>Tamworth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <add>march .25.</add> 
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Abel Roper,</hi> at the Sun againſt S. <hi>Dunſtans</hi> Church in <hi>Fleet-ſtreet.</hi> 1658.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:119052:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:119052:2"/>
            <head>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>depiction of the four evangelists and their symbols (Matthew, angel; Mark, lion; Luke, ox; and John, eagle) with the Paraclete (as a dove) occupying the central position in the depiction</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </head>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>READER,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat I might ſatisfie the deſire of ſome worthy Freinds, I do here preſent unto thee a Sermon (with very little alteration) preached at the Funerall of that Godly and Learned Miniſter of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> Mr. <hi>Blake,</hi> now with God: Being the rather induced thereunto, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I know the memory of his Name, will be very gratefull and welcome to ſuch who were acquainted with him. How ſadly his death was laid to heart, the deportment of many at that time did abundantly manifeſt, and Although I cannot ſpeak the ſame which <hi>Nazianzen</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmeth concerning the Funeral ſolemnities of <hi>Baſil,</hi> how that many thouſands were there
<pb facs="tcp:119052:3"/> preſent, ſome whereof by the violent preſs were killed, being happy in this (as he Rhetorica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth) that they dyed with him, as alſo that Jews and Heathens did strive with Christians, who ſhould pour out greater plenty of Tears, yet ſo many declared their Affections by weeping eyes, that we may ſay, Behold how they loved him. But I forbear this ſad ſubject. The Lord Christ, that chief Shepherd of ſouls provide for his Church ſucceſſively in all ages ſuch Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors, who ſhall feed his People after his own mind, and that with Truth, Zeal and Concord they may be found doing his work, when their Maſter ſhall come.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Sutton-Coldfield, <date>Octob. 19. 1657.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Thy ſouls well-willer, <hi>Anthony Burgeſſe.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:119052:3"/>
            <head>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>depiction of the four evangelists and their symbols (Matthew, angel; Mark, lion; Luke, ox; and John, eagle) with the Paraclete (as a dove) occupying the central position in the depiction</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </head>
            <head>A SERMON At the FUNERAL of the Reverend Mr. <hi>Thomas Blake,</hi> Miniſter of the GOSPEL.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>ACTS 20. 36, 37, 38.</bibl>
               <q>
                  <p>And when he had thus ſpoken, he kneeled on the ground, and prayed with them all:</p>
                  <p>And they all wept ſore, and fell on <hi>Pauls</hi> neck, and kiſſed him;</p>
                  <p>Sorrowing moſt of all for the words which he ſpake, that they ſhould ſee his face no more.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>IN the latter part of this Chapter, we have <hi>Paul</hi> making his own Funeral Sermon; and the words of a <hi>dying Paſtor,</hi> whoſe Face they ſhall never ſee more, are to be like <hi>goads and nails,</hi> yea, <hi>fiery nails,</hi> as the <hi>Septuagint</hi> render it, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 12. 11. And this
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:119052:4"/> valedictory Sermon, we know not whether the <hi>matter,</hi> or the <hi>affection</hi> in the delivering of it, be more admirable: It's milk that cometh hot from the breaſt; excellent matter, without hearty af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>f<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ctions, is like a Meſſenger without feet, and a Bird without wings. I ſhall not make a Sermon upon his Sermon, onely in the general; by that diſcourſe we have a deſcription of a <hi>Paſtor</hi> and <hi>Officer</hi> in the Church, <hi>in Idea</hi> and <hi>in ſubjecto: In Idea,</hi> or in the <hi>Theſi,</hi> there the Apoſtle deſcribeth ſuch by their name and titles, they are <hi>Overſeers</hi> and <hi>Elders, v.</hi> 17. from the <hi>efficient cauſe</hi> the Holy Ghoſt hath made them ſo, from the <hi>relation they are in:</hi> The People are their Flock, and they are Gods Church. And laſtly, from the <hi>dignity and high thoughts put upon them by Chriſt,</hi> they were purchaſed with his own blood, ſhall we think our labor, our pains our ſweat, too much, when Chriſt thought not his blood too much?</p>
            <p>To enter upon the Controverſie who theſe <hi>El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> and <hi>Overſeers</hi> were<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> is repugnant to the occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion at this time: Then you have this office <hi>in ſubje<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>to, in Hypotheſi;</hi> in the practice of it, you have the rule of a <hi>Paſtor,</hi> and the example of a <hi>Ruler,</hi> and that is in <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf: O the <hi>zeal, watchful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> the <hi>dilegence,</hi> the <hi>courage,</hi> the <hi>purity</hi> of <hi>aime</hi> and <hi>ends,</hi> which he profeſſeth in his Miniſterial diſcharge! not that he ſpeaketh theſe for oſtenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but imitation; for he would not have ſaid thus much of himſelf, ſaith <hi>Grotius</hi> on the place, but that hereby he would leave a <hi>patern</hi> or <hi>form of life</hi> to all ſucceſſors; Inſomuch, that no Miniſter
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:119052:4"/> reading <hi>Pauls</hi> expreſſions of himſelf in this place, but may cry out, O me! a clod of earth to ſuch a Star, Ice to ſuch a Fire, a worm to ſuch an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel! Though he were a <hi>Paul,</hi> as ſome think his name denoteth, little in ſtature of his body, yet he was a Gyant in Gifts and Graces, ſo that Papiſts themſelves cannot but give the pre-eminence to <hi>Paul</hi> above <hi>Peter,</hi> in reſpect of Doctrine and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterial abilities: He was the <hi>earthly Angel,</hi> the <hi>Cor Chriſti,</hi> the <hi>Tuba Evangelii,</hi> as the Ancients call him; yet I am not of <hi>Amyraldus</hi> his minde, <hi>conſider.</hi> in <hi>cap.</hi> 7. <hi>ad Rom.</hi> who denying the Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation of the ſeventh of the <hi>Romans,</hi> to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood perſonally of <hi>Paul,</hi> thinking this would be injurious to the Grace of God ſanctifying of him, and making him ſo eminent a Servant in his Church: He affirmeth, that if God pleaſed ſo to adorn <hi>Paul</hi> with the gifts of the Spirit, that he ſhould in this life arrive at that fulneſs and perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of holineſs, which other Believers obtain no where but in Heaven, that thereby he might be propounded as a perfect example to all Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, and his Miniſtry be more happily efficacious; here was not (ſaith he) any thing to be blame-worthy: But though we grant <hi>Paul</hi> to have an el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Brothers portion in the Graces and Gifts of Chriſt, ſo that if no Miniſter could be ſaved, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs he were a <hi>Paul,</hi> wo be to us all; yet that <hi>Paul</hi> was not above the combate of the fleſh and ſpirit within him, appeareth partly <hi>in that careful</hi> keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing down of his body, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9. 27. leſt ſin ſhould prevail; as alſo in thoſe buffetings of Satan which
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:119052:5"/> he was exerciſed with, that he might not be lifted up above meaſure, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. 7. Well, however it be, the Apoſtle having both by rule and exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, as you heard deſcribed what a Miniſter or Paſtor is to be, we have the conſequent of this in my Text: When he had thus ſpoken, thus of himſelf, and thus of a Goſpel-Miniſter, he kneel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed down and prayed.</p>
            <p>There are two actions of the body mentioned in Prayer, which denote that excellent deport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that ſhould be at that time in the ſoul; kneel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the body, that denoteth ſelf-humiliation; lifting up the hands, that implieth faith and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence: Thus <hi>deſcendendo aſcenditur,</hi> how hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly do the people of God keep theſe two Graces co-operating together, but either their Humilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion abateth their Faith, or their Faith hindreth their Humiliation; both theſe together are the <hi>Calidum</hi> and the <hi>Humidum,</hi> which maintain the life of holy Duties; be Prayed as well as kneeled, for that is the onely key to open Heaven, that is <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vids</hi> Harp, to allay all thoſe unruly affections that are apt to diſturb us.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, here is the effect of all upon the Audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, which is expreſſed, Firſt, In their paſſion of weeping, with the aggravation. 1. <hi>They wept ſore.</hi> 2. Their great love, <hi>They fell on Pauls neck and kiſſed him.</hi> 3. The motive of all this affectionate carriage, That which did open theſe Flood-gates, it was becauſe <hi>they ſhould ſee his face no more;</hi> they ſhould for ever loſe him, enjoy no more of his Miniſterial Labors and diligence: now this is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:119052:5"/> by the Evangeliſt, as a commendation; It was a ſpirituall, not a naturall weeping; It was not like weeping for a dead Father, or a dead Wife, but for a dead Paſtor, by whoſe ſpirituall labours their ſouls had made great proficiency; I ſhall from theſe words obſerve two doctrines ſuitable to the two conſiderable parts of this auditory, the one ſeaſonable for the <hi>Miniſters of the Goſpel</hi> here preſent, The other opportune for the <hi>Congregation of Tamworth,</hi> now bereaved of a <hi>faithful Paſtor,</hi> whom I may ſee <hi>mourning</hi> and <hi>weeping,</hi> and that <hi>moſt of all,</hi> becauſe <hi>you ſhall ſee his face no more,</hi> you ſhall not behold him in this place again, you ſhall not hear his voice from hence again. The firſt Obſervation is grounded upon theſe words, <hi>when he had thus ſpoken,</hi> This about the <hi>duty of a Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster,</hi> This about <hi>his Holy, Godly,</hi> and <hi>exemplary con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation;</hi> From whence obſerve,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That a faithful diſcharge of the miniſteriall Office doth bring unſpeakable comfort to ſuch as can upon juſt grounds aſſume this to themſelves;</hi> From this faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs we ſee often <hi>Paul</hi> receiving a great deal of comfort. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. 6, 7, 8. The time of his departure was at hand; doth not this then make him afraid? how ſhall he give an account concerning the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement of his talents? No, <hi>I have fought a good fight, I have finiſhed my courſe, &amp;c.</hi> We have the like glorious profeſſion made by this holy Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2, 3, 4, 5, 6. which is an excellent Copy for every Miniſter to write after, to live and breathe from thence; and in this he is ſo cleare, that he ſaith, <hi>Ye are witneſſes,</hi> and God alſo, how
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:119052:6"/> 
               <hi>holily, juſtly</hi> and <hi>unblameably, we have behaved our ſelves amongſt thoſe that beleeve.</hi> But yet let none think that <hi>Paul</hi> doth thus magnifie inherent grace, to exclude imputed grace, for 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. 4. Though he ſaith, he knoweth nothing by himſelf, yet he concludeth, <hi>I am not thereby juſtified, but he that judgeth me is the Lord,</hi> he knew more evill in <hi>Paul,</hi> then <hi>Paul</hi> him ſelf could do, and certainly, ſo great is this miniſterial work, that <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf cryed out, <hi>Who is ſufficient for theſe things? Chryſoſtome</hi> hath very diſcouraging paſſages, as if few Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters could be ſaved, but his meaning muſt be, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe few are carefull, zealous, and diligent; O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe ſuch as <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> himſelf, that is ſaid to fear nothing but ſin, and thoſe that by their Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrin and life, turn many from iniquities, ſhall have more then ordinary glory in heaven; To ampli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie this, I ſhall in ſome <hi>particulars</hi> or Characters deſcribe how, or when the Miniſtery is faithfully diſcharged, what is ingredient thereunto, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituent thereof; And firſt there is required <hi>an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward experimental ſavory work of grace upon the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters own heart,</hi> that thereby he may more <hi>affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onately</hi> and <hi>cordially</hi> deal with others; when we know the terror of the Lord, and the love of Chriſt experimentally, this maketh us able in the work of the Miniſtery, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 1<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. I doe not ſay that the Office of a Miniſter is null, if he be not a regenerate man, or as if he were no Miniſter, or might not be uſefull in the Church of God, but as to himſelf, he cannot faithfully diſcharge this Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, ſo as to obtaine a crown of glory hereafter,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:119052:6"/> unleſs he be thus qualified; There is <hi>Theologia ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiocinativa</hi> and <hi>experimentalis,</hi> as <hi>Gerſon</hi> ſpeaketh, A man may know things, as <hi>Aquinas</hi> ſaith, <hi>per mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum cognitionis,</hi> or, <hi>per modum inclinationis;</hi> now it is this experimental Divinitie, that worketh be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides Knowledge an inclination and propenſitie to the thing known, that maketh us able to diſcharge this duty; To Preach of Regeneration, of Faith, when a man hath no ſavory underſtanding of theſe things, is to talk of the ſweetneſs of honey, when we never taſted it, or of the excellency of ſuch a Countrey, which we never were in, but know it by Mapps only. If thou knoweſt the truths of God, but by Books, by Authors onely, and thy own heart feeleth not the power of theſe things, Thou art but as the Conduit, that letteth out wine or refreſhing water to others, but thou thy ſelf taſteſt not of it, or like the hand that directeth the Paſſenger, but thou thy ſelf ſtandeſt ſtill.</p>
            <p>2. To a faithfull diſcharge, there is required a <hi>ſound knowledge, judgement</hi> and <hi>skill in divine things;</hi> hence they are called <hi>lights, guides,</hi> and <hi>Shepherds,</hi> they are required to be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 2. <hi>apt to teach, to reprove in all Doctrine.</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. 2. It is not enough to cry out of Hereſies or of ſinnes, unleſs we rebuke with doctrine; The leaſt Knowledge that <hi>Caſuiſts</hi> condeſcend unto in a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter is, that he muſt be learned, <hi>ſupra vulgus fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lium:</hi> Is he a fit Miniſter that can onely Preach and pray by a preſcript, or form from another? He is not a fit Phyſitian, or a fit Lawyer, that ſhould doe ſo in his way; Miniſters therefore ſhould take
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:119052:7"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:119052:7"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:119052:8"/> that exhortation, which we ſee <hi>Paul</hi> gave even to <hi>Timothy,</hi> though ſo well accompliſhed. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. 15. <hi>Meditate upon theſe things, give thy ſelf wholly to them, that thy profiting may appear,</hi> yea, <hi>verſ.</hi> 13. <hi>Till I come, give attendance to reading.</hi> The cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance of time is to be obſerved, for though <hi>Paul</hi> was to come ſhortly to him, yet that little time he was abſent from <hi>Paul,</hi> muſt be improved in reading Gods Word. Be thou a ſcribe inſtruct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for the Kingdome of heaven, that can bring out of thy treaſure, old and new; be a Fountain, not a Ceſtern, that will quickly be dry; <hi>Cajetan Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mula, Tit. Doctoratus,</hi> maketh it a mortall ſinne to approve any for a Doctor in Divinitie, who is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably inſufficient, becauſe hereby he is teſtified to be a Phyſitian of ſouls, when yet through his ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance, may be the ruine of many; I dare not avouch that of <hi>Luther,</hi> who ſaid it is a German Proverb, <hi>that young Divines fill Hell,</hi> onely it is a good warning, that ſuch be diligent in ſtudying, that God may bleſſe them with all knowledge and underſtanding, firſt in the Scripture, and then in all other parts of Divinitie, whether controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall, poſitive or practicall, eſpecially adde to thy Miniſteriall knowledge theſe two things; Firſt <hi>a firm faith,</hi> for to read and to know much, but not to digeſt it, maketh us ſcepticall; Have faith, not reaſon or opinion in religious things, <hi>Calvin</hi> ſaith in <hi>Comment.</hi> 2. <hi>Epiſt. ad Corin.</hi> that the Miniſters of of God, who go up into the Pulpit in the name of Chriſt, to preach his Word, ought to have ſuch firmneſs of Faith in them, that they are aſſured
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:119052:8"/> that their Doctrine can no more be overthrowne, then God himſelf; now truely, this faith is much to be commended to us, we may have much lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, much reading, but little Faith, be very ſcep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall, and deale in Divinitie as we uſe to do in Philoſophy, <hi>videtur quod ſic, videtur quod non,</hi> Great Schollars are not alwayes great beleevers, The want of this maketh a man of a <hi>Socinian</hi> faith, an <hi>Arminian</hi> faith, a Popiſh faith, as often as any plauſible Argument, or carnal Intereſt interpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth.</p>
            <p>2. With this knowledge labour much after <hi>Caſuiſticall Divinity,</hi> whereby you may be able to direct the tempted in caſes of Conſcience, To guide the afflicted in ſoul, what they are to doe; Indeed the Papiſts have a deale of Caſuiſticall di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinitie in large voluminous diſcourſes, but it is for the moſt part calculated according to their meridians of ſuperſtitious uſages and Cuſtomes, but it is pitty that among us <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſall Bookes are farre more then our caſuiſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call, yet remember the Scripture calleth it, <hi>the tongue of the Learned, Iſa.</hi> 50. 4. <hi>To know how to ſpeak a word in ſeaſon to him that is weary;</hi> The wounds of Conſcience are the moſt tender, and therefore require a Spirituall skilfull Phyſitian. The Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences of men are the ſubject matter of your Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, and therefore look after that <hi>Ars Cordis,</hi> which is indeed a liberall art that will ſet us free.</p>
            <p>3. He that will faithfully diſcharge the Office of his Miniſtery, muſt regard the <hi>end of it,</hi> the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:119052:9"/> 
               <hi>finis operis,</hi> and <hi>finis operantis,</hi> the <hi>finis miniſterii,</hi> and <hi>miniſtri,</hi> muſt be all one: The end of the Miniſtry is to exalt God &amp; Chriſt, to dethrone Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan, to bring many out of their ſins unto the obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience of the Goſpel: Now if a man aim at other things in his Miniſtry then this he can never com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortably diſcharge it: To be a Miniſter for earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly profits, for ambition and vain glory, theſe will be like the gravel, that will preſently ſtop the Ship in its paſſage; and truly herein we may much lament our entrance in to this work, how many ſet upon it as a profeſſion to live upon, by that they hope to ſatisfie their needs, but if this end and motive do ſtill reign in thee, it will be like a milſtone about thy neck; outward maintenance may be a ſecondary end, but not the principal; ſtill then awe thy ſoul with the end of thy office, that all other knowledge is exerciſed about the body, or mens Eſtates, or the nature of things; but thine is Theology, <hi>De Deo, à Deo, in Deum,</hi> its concerning God objectively, its from God effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctively, its to God finally.</p>
            <p>4. He that will faithfully diſcharge this Office of the Miniſtry, muſt as <hi>Paul</hi> profeſſeth, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 12. <hi>have his converſation with all godly ſimplicity and ſincerity:</hi> He is to carry on his work in Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture-ways, avoiding thoſe two Rocks, <hi>Media violentiae,</hi> and <hi>Media fraudulentiae;</hi> A man of a crafty multiplicity of Spirit, will turn into any ſhape, diſpute for any thing as lawful: This the Jeſuit ſaid to one (for ſo I underſtand it) who doubted about ſomething he was to do, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:119052:9"/> lawful or no, <hi>Aude</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>&amp; nos efficiemus probabile, Janſen. St. Auguſt. lib. proaem. pag.</hi> 9. Be daring to do it, and we will make it probable; now this ſimplicity of Spirit in Miniſterial im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment, is greatly ſeen in an obediential depend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance upon the word of God, whether in matter of Duty, or of Faith: What is it that maketh ſo many learned Men embrace Errors after Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, but becauſe they leave Faith, and attend to reaſon? They think we come to be Chriſtians by Diſputations and ſcientifical Demonſtrations; as we come to be Philoſophers, not by a ſingle and plain captivating of our underſtandings to the ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, whereas it is Chriſtian Faith, nor Chriſtian reaſon: It is ſaid to be <hi>Nazianzens</hi> Emblem, <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ologia noſtra eſt Pythagorica,</hi> by this ſimplicity of Spirit, a man ſhall overcome thoſe Temptations, which are uſually in Scholars to bring, <hi>inaudita &amp; inviſa,</hi> ſtrange and unheard things unto our Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; eſpecially let the Miniſters of the Goſpel be ſo guided by ſimplicity of Spirit, that they may a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void theſe three Rocks.</p>
            <p>Firſt, that while they avoid a Popiſh blinde o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience to men, examining things by Scripture, they therefore do not make all things uncertain: That of <hi>Durand</hi> is true, whoſoever forſaketh reaſon becauſe of humane Authority, <hi>incidit in inſipientiam beſtialem,</hi> maketh himſelf like a Beaſt; yet let not this liberty be abuſed to licentiouſneſs, to believe nothing, to deſpiſe all thoſe Miniſterial helps which God hath vouchſafed to the Church, becauſe he is to try all things; though he muſt
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:119052:10"/> try, yet he muſt not be always trying, <hi>but hold faſt that which is good,</hi> 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5. 21. This liberty and particular Judgement of diſcerning, which God alloweth every man, is not to be oppoſed to that deciſive Miniſterial Judgement, which God hath appointed in his Church.</p>
            <p>Secondly, under pretence of a more moderate and impartial handling of things, as not being ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted unto parties, take heed thou do not make a party of thy ſelf, as the Sect of Philoſophers, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Diogen. Laert. in Proem.</hi> pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they would be of no Sect, but chooſe the beſt Art of all; thus they made a Sect, while they condemned all.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, Take heed of being deceived under the pretence that thou doeſt not bring in any new matter, but new words, or thou doſt digeſt things into a better method; for by this means, men leaving that ſimplicity and Scripture-dependance they once had, have corrupted their Miniſterial Office, inſtead of a faithful diſcharge of it.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, To a faithful diſcharge of this dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Office, there is required an excellent com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound <hi>of many choice Graces,</hi> inſomuch that a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters qualification, is like that Ointment that was to be made for the Prieſt onely: There muſt be love and compaſſion to Peoples Souls, which was abundantly diſcovered in our Savior himſelf: <hi>Paul</hi> compareth himſelf, ſometimes to a Father, ſometimes to a Mother, ſometimes to a Nurſe, becauſe of this affectionate deſire in him: There muſt be Zeal, Fortitude, and Courage, the <hi>ſpirit</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:119052:10"/> 
               <hi>of love and of power alſo;</hi> he is not a Miniſter, that is not <hi>ad mille mortes paratus,</hi> ſaid <hi>Chryſoſtome; as a good Souldier endure hardſhip,</hi> ſaith <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 3. There muſt be Prudence and Wiſdom, elſe Love and Power will make us like <hi>Sampſon,</hi> without eyes; there muſt be ſalt in the Sacrifice, as well as fire; <hi>Oportet Paſtor ſit totus ocu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lus,</hi> a Paſtor muſt be an <hi>Argus,</hi> full of eyes.</p>
            <p>Again, there muſt be an <hi>Heavemly heart,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temning the world and all earthly advantages: The eye that is to ſee for others muſt not have duſt falling into it: <hi>Auſtin</hi> maketh an Heretick to have ſome carnal profit or emolument that is at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractive of him: There muſt be a <hi>deſire to pleaſe God, and not men,</hi> as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Gal.</hi> 1. for ſo a man cannot be a ſervant of Chriſt: This fear to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſe men, whereby we do not reprove ſin ſo Zealouſly, ſo Cordially and Faithfully as we ſhould, hath eclipſed the comfort of ſome godly Miniſters at their death. It is too true that the Wiſe man ſaith, <hi>The fear of a man is his ſnare, Prov.</hi> 29. 25. The Camelion for fear, ſaith <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtotle,</hi> turneth into the likeneſs of every object it meeteth with.</p>
            <p>Theſe are the ſpecial qualifications of a Godly Miniſter, whereby he will be able to ſay with <hi>Paul, I have fought a good fight.</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. 7. Yea, with <hi>CHRIST, I have finiſhed the worke thou gaveſt me to do, John</hi> 17. 3. To all which muſt be added <hi>diligence</hi> and <hi>labour,</hi> all the names, they have denote labour more then glory, office more then dignitie; now in all theſe things there is one particular,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:119052:11"/> which doth much quicken, and that is <hi>temptation,</hi> one of thoſe three things, <hi>Luther</hi> ſaid, made a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine; we are not to deſire temptations, but God for the moſt part doth prepare thoſe Miniſters, whom he intends to be ſerviceable, by ſuch exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſes; This is the ſawing, and the poliſhing of the ſtone, by this he is brought into the deep wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and ſeeth the wonderfull works of God, by this he is able to underſtand the depths of Satan, and by this he is adapted to be a moſt ſpeciall In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument to comfort and refreſh others, when they ſhall ſee theirs is not a ſingular condition, they muſt not think none are tempted like them, for they ſhall find that even <hi>Pauls</hi> have had the buffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of Satan, and that by theſe foule temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons they have learned more then all Books or au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors could teach them. And thus I leave the firſt Doctrine, and proceed to the ſecond, which is.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>2</label> 
               <hi>That a Godly People cannot but affectionately mourn under the loſſe of their faithfull Miniſters.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You ſee here what theſe <hi>Epheſians</hi> did, with what affection they were moved, becauſe they ſhould never ſee <hi>Pauls</hi> face more; Grace doth not lie in extinguiſhing, but regulating affections; <hi>Chriſt wept,</hi> and they argued from thence, <hi>behold how he loved him, Joh,</hi> 11. 35, 26. So that <hi>Nazian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens</hi> commendation of his Mother <hi>Nonna,</hi> that ſhe never wept under the many troubles ſhe under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>went, ſubmitting all to Gods hand, was rather Stoiciſme, then Chriſtianitie; It is ſaid of <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe,</hi> when he heard of the death of any good
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:119052:11"/> Miniſter, he could not forbeare weeping; how then can a people forbeare, when their own Miniſter, their own Paſtor is taken away, ſhould not the Congregation be a valley of tears, or a place of mourners; now there are theſe grounds for it, 1. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of that experimentall ſoul-good, and ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all advantage the Godly have reapt thereby; Oh! when thou ſhalt remember what quicknings, what meltings, what warming of heart thou haſt had, this will cauſe grief to think they are gone. Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall naturall men never are affected with the loſſe of a Miniſter, they never got any good by their Preaching; it was no converting Miniſtry, no in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightning, no comforting Miniſtry to them, and therefore the loſs is no more troubleſome.</p>
            <p>2. They muſt needs mourn, becauſe they have juſt cauſe to fear, their ſinnes have cauſed God to deprive them of ſuch helps; your unthankfulneſs, your contempt, and low thoughts of the means of grace, your unprofitableneſs and negligence, may make you mourn, for if God upon the abuſe of naturall Creatures, will take away his Wine, his Bread, his flaxe, will he not much more remove the candleſtick, for unfruitfulneſs under ſpiritual mercies; mourne then, leſt thy ſinnes, thy un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faithfulneſs, thy deadneſs and dulneſs of heart have provoked God to take ſuch guides away; yea in the third place, may not ſome mourn, who by their Diſobedience, and unwillingneſſe to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to Chriſts yoak, and oppoſition to his way, have ſo filled the Miniſters heart with grief and ſadneſs, as thereby to haſten his death, making
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:119052:12"/> his life the more uncomfortable, and cauſing him to mourn in ſecret for your ſtubbornneſs and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience; Thus your ſinnes, not only meritori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, but efficiently may concurre to the remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of him by death; Conſider that place. <hi>Heb.</hi> 13. 17. <hi>Obey them that rule over you, &amp;c. that they may give their account with joy, and not with grief;</hi> ſome make this particular to relate to the former, that they may watch over your ſouls with joy, and not with grief, for that is unprofitable for you. A grieved Miniſter, a diſcouraged Miniſter cannot do his duty, ſo powerfully, it will be unprofitable unto you, you will find it in his ſtudy, in his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons; A dull people are apt to make a dull Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter.</p>
            <p>4. There is cauſe to mourn, becauſe of the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencie of the relation between a Paſtor and a People, in ſome reſpects, it is above all natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall relations. They are ſpirituall Fathers, your ſouls receive good by them; They are Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall to bring you unto eternal glory, and therefore there is more cauſe of Mourning in this reſpect, then when God breaketh naturall rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, no Father or Mother, or friend happily hath done that for thee which his Miniſtery hath done.</p>
            <p>5. There is cauſe to mourn, becauſe it is a ſign of Gods anger and diſpleaſure to a people, you are not ſo much to look upon it; as the loſſe of a man, as a token of Gods anger to the congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation; <hi>The righteous man periſheth, and none layeth it to heart. Iſaiah.</hi> 57. 1. Who knoweth what ſoul-Judgments,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:119052:12"/> what bodily Judgements may hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter come vpon you, and therefore it is for a peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to be ſenſible, and mourn, when the deſire of your eies, ſo I may call the Miniſter (as well as the Wife) is taken away. The deſire of your eies, you long to ſee him in the Pulpit again, and the deſire of your eares, you long to heare him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain.</p>
            <p>6. There is cauſe to Mourn, becauſe of the ſad conſequents that many times falls upon the death of a faithfull Paſtor; ſometimes the learning and ſoundneſs of a Miniſter, keepeth a People from licentious errors and corrupt opinions; His Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitie and Pietie hath a ſpeciall influence upon ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, but upon his removall, then the weeds of a mans heart growes up: <hi>After my departure,</hi> ſaith <hi>Paul, Wolves will ariſe from among your ſelves, Acts</hi> 20. 29. <hi>Pauls</hi> preſence was a great means to hinder them.</p>
            <p>2. What good Foundation is laid in Faith, what Godly Order may be begun? there is danger, that all theſe will die, when a Faithfull Miniſter dieth: <hi>I wonder that you are ſo ſoon removed,</hi> ſaith <hi>Paul, Gal.</hi> 1. Alas! that which the Miniſters of God have with many years diligence, many Prayers, and much oppoſition brought about, when the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter is dead, may quickly be deſtroyed, ſo that we may wonder, how ſuch a Town, ſuch a place ſhould be over-run with Bryars and Thornes im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately.</p>
            <p>3. Another ſad conſequent is ſometimes, divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions and breaches among the People, while a
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:119052:13"/> Godly Miniſter is alive, he is like a Corner Stone, that uniteth both ſides of the Wall together, but when that falls, then the wall falls with it. Then one is for this Miniſter, and another for that, then one liketh this, and another the contrary, and thus ſeeds of contention and diviſion are ſowen, which may come up too faſt, hence the preſence of a Godly, Grave, Wiſe Paſtor is very neceſſary, it is the Spirituall defence of a People, which made him cry out, when the Prophet was taken, <hi>My fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, my Father, the Chariots of Iſrael, and the horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men thereof.</hi> 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 13. 14. And now we come from the Doctrinal part to the practicall; And although my cuſtome in ſuch Sermons, is not to diſcourſe about the Dead, they being like Anato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my Lectures, for the good of the living, yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we are celebrating the Funeralls of a Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and Godly Brother, who by his Office, was in publick ſtation in the Church of God; I ſhall brief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſpeak to ſome few of thoſe Miniſteriall qualifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations, that were in him mentioned in the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, not imitating <hi>Nazianzen,</hi> who in his Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall Orations of his Father, as alſo <hi>Athanaſius, Baſilius</hi> and others induſtriouſly gathereth up eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing that may make to their praiſe, if not hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perbolically exceeding ſometimes; but I ſhall ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther come ſhort of what might be ſpoken. And firſt, his Doctrinall abilities, and parts in contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vsrſall points, are ſufficiently known by the Books he hath written; thoſe Children will reſemble the Father, though he left no bodily ones. It is true, there were ſome particular opinions and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſts
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:119052:13"/> he was fallen into with other Learned men, on whoſe ſide the truth did ſtand, you will not judge it meet for me to interpoſe, onely becauſe of the difference that is ſometimes in Judgement between Godly men, we ſee ſome by profaneneſs, gladly have it in their mouthes, ſaying, what heed is to be given to theſe Miniſters, there are not two of a minde; They write againſt one another, they have Book againſt Book, and then ſome good people they are offended; what ſhall we do, ſay they, we look upon both as Godly, and yet they cannot agree; becauſe I ſay, of this offence, I ſhall ſpeak a little to it. Firſt, that this difference a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt our ſelves, is an old objection, The <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans</hi> and the <hi>Jewes</hi> urged it againſt Chriſtianity, whoſe Arguments <hi>Clemens Alexandrinus</hi> anſwered, retorting upon them the ſame diviſions; the <hi>Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophers</hi> likewiſe objected this to the Chriſtians, when that <hi>Synod</hi> was gathered together at <hi>Nice,</hi> as the Centuriators inform us; Though <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine (lib. de vera religione)</hi> brandeth them for this, that the Heathens, though they had divers ſchools, yet they had <hi>Commune Templum,</hi> a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon temple, which argued, they worſhipped their Gods more out of Cuſtome, then becauſe of their opinion.</p>
            <p>2. We are to know, that all the Godly do know onely in part, perfection in knowledge, and unity is reſerved for heaven; there will be no parties, no dividing opinions, there will be no different Forms, and wayes of worſhipping of God in that place, ſo that although this difference amongſt the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:119052:14"/> Godly be as <hi>Calvin</hi> ſaid to <hi>Melancthon, peſſimi ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empli,</hi> of a very bad example, yet if we conſider, that the meaſure of Light &amp; grace in this world is imperfect, then we may not wonder at ſuch brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches; had not <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> a Paroxiſme, a ſharp fitt, for to underſtand the Word in a good ſenſe, as ſome would, becauſe the Word is uſed ſo. <hi>Heb.</hi> 10. 24. is very improbable. <hi>Auſtin</hi> and <hi>Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome, Chryſoſtome</hi> and <hi>Epiphanius</hi> had great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſts.</p>
            <p>3. The differences of Godly Miniſters are not in fundamentals; They all build gold and preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſtones, though ſome may adde hay and ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble</p>
            <p>Laſtly, a brotherly and amicable diſquiſition into truths controverſed, not fundamentall, but between Godly men, though different in Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, is very lawfull and uſefull, indeed if this be done with pride, paſſion, ſcornfull and diſdainfull words, deſpiſing the gifts of others, This is not a dead fly, but a dead toad in the box of ointment, that maketh the wiſe Reader think, men do re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard opinions, not ſo much as they are Gods Truths, but as they are their opinions, wherein they muſt have glory; But return we to our Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Brother; as God had given him ſuch Doctri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Abilities, ſo alſo was he Prudent and Wiſe, and wiſe to direct ſuch as were troubled in their minde, and perplexed about what they were to doe; It is true, it pleaſed God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his ſickneſs to exerciſe him with ſome ſad
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:119052:14"/> and black thoughts, ſometimes tending to the great dejection and diſcouragement of his ſoul, but by this we ſee, that comfort is not a flower growing in our Garden, that we can pluck up when we will, God is the God of Comfort only, he giveth it when he pleaſeth, and he taketh it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way again as he pleaſeth. Chriſt had an Angel to comfort him in his Agonies, ſo that all, both Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters and People, are to take Goſpel-Conſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as mercies from heaven, not as the work of our hands.</p>
            <p>In the next place, the diligence, conſtancy and faithfull Preaching of your Godly Paſtor is not unknown; Theſe walls, theſe ſeats can ſufficiently beare witneſs thereunto; Though you a great People, and he declining in age, yet a laborious Preacher to you, and a great Student in private: The Catechizing alſo of the younger ſort of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, diſcovered his vigilancy, and it was the ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt deſire (as he would have you informed) and requeſt of your dying Paſtor, that the younger Perſons of this place would readily and willingly ſubmit to that order; Beſides all this, his writing for the publick good of the Church, ſtill demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated his faithfulneſs and zeal herein; when the Perſecutor had cut out <hi>Cyprians</hi> tongue, and then baniſhed him, yet he made a ſupply by his Pen; but our Learned Brother was willing both by Tongue and Pen to edifie the Church of God, ſo that both his <hi>opuſcula,</hi> and his <hi>opera</hi> will praiſe him in the gates, <hi>His tenderneſs of Spirit</hi> likewiſe was exceeding much; and as in ſoft wood, wormes
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:119052:15"/> ſometimes breed to weaken it, ſo did (as you heard) diſcouragements ſometimes lie upon his ſoul, but the Lord did quickly blow over the clouds, and as I am informed, his expreſſion was, <hi>That he dyed with full ſatisfaction of Spirit, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, you are not ignorant of the way he took about the Sacrament, that he was not for the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſcuous Admiſſion of all thereunto; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore when a late Writer, Mr. <hi>Humphreys,</hi> would have gathered ſuch concluſions from his prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, he was willing publickly to vindicate him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and to ſhew his diſſent herein; All this, though comparatively little, I have ſpoken, not to exalt man, for what have we, that we have not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, but to bleſs God, and magnifie him, who giveth ſuch gifts to men; he that praiſeth the gifts and graces of any, thereby extolleth God; as he that commendeth a Picture, magnifieth the Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficer that made it; and thus we take our dear and laſt farewell of him, and come to you, ſheep left without a ſhepheard, to you on the Sea without a Pilate; To you Orphans, without a Spirituall Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; and firſt you ſee what cauſe there is for our conſtant expectation and preparation for death; Gods own Miniſters and ſervants muſt dye, God needeth no mans labours or parts, <hi>Moſes, Joſhua, Paul, Peter</hi> muſt die, <hi>ſola mors non habet fortaſſe,</hi> ſaid <hi>Auſtin,</hi> only Death hath no may be; It may be thou mayeſt be rich, it may be thou mayeſt thrive in thy trading, it may be thou mayeſt have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:119052:15"/> in thy Children and friends, but thy death hath no may be; Oh! let not the world, let not your Shops, let not trading take off your hearts from this Meditation, but think you hear God ſpeaking to you, ſet not your houſe, but your ſouls in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, for thou muſt die.</p>
            <p>And ſecondly, here is ſome comfort, though there be cauſe of much ſorrow, that though your Faithfull Paſtor he dead, yet the chief Paſtor of your ſouls is not; He that ſetteth Paſtors and Teachers in the Church, he that ſendeth forth la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourers into his harveſt, he liveth for ever; as one in the Eccleſiaſticall Hiſtory, when newes was brought him that his father was dead, <hi>Deſine blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mias loqui</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>pater enim meus immortalis eſt,</hi> ceaſe to ſpeak blaſphemy, for my Father is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortall; Thus let this honey fall into your gall, this Wine into your water, The great and Chief Shepheard of your ſouls is not dead.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, now the will of God is done, concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our deceaſed Brother, your duty is to be much in <hi>Prayer</hi> to God, that there may be a <hi>Joſhua</hi> after <hi>Moſes,</hi> That God would <hi>joyne your hearts together as one man,</hi> to ſeek out a Paſtor for you, which ſhall feed you according to his holy will; The Lord hath made a great breach upon you, be ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible of it, and ſeriouſly conſider how all your ſoul-comforts and advantages are bound up in this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; Miniſters are compared to the Sun, and Salt, <hi>nihilſole &amp; ſale utilius;</hi> can you be without the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:119052:16"/> Sun in the heavens? without bread for your bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, ſo neither without this bread of life for your ſouls, or without this light to guide you in the wilderneſſe of this World, to eternall happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="funeral_oration">
            <pb facs="tcp:119052:16"/>
            <head>A Funerall <hi>Oration</hi> at the Death of the moſt deſired Mr. <hi>Blake.</hi>
            </head>
            <byline>By <hi>Mr. Samuel Shaw,</hi> then School-maſter of the Free-School at <hi>Tamworth.</hi>
            </byline>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Ith a face ſadder then uſuall, with an heart ſadder then my face, but upon an occaſion ſadder then them both, I (who was deputed to this work by him to whom I now per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form it) am here, rather to receive the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions of your ſorrow, then tell you the reſentments of mine own. Being ſenſible of my ſtupefaction, (cauſed, not through the want of my affections, but the want of their object) I deſire out of a pious pollicy, to ſupply my dryneſſe, by taking your Tears, and putting them into my pump, ſo hoping to revive mine own, which yet I judge are rather drowned then dryed up. And yet when I have done this, I know that all my expreſſions will fall ſhort of the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of my grief, as much as my grief does of the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of its cauſe. This numerous Company of Pious groan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, theſe ſo many blacks, not made, but occaſioned to be Mourners (badges of profeſſion becomming badges of that grief, which for its greatneſs can be equal'd by nothing but their former happineſs which they once enjoyed) the univerſall gloomineſs of this day, repreſents to me rather the funerall of a Town, then a man, and the fall of a Church, rather then a ſingle pillar: and rather induces
<pb facs="tcp:119052:17"/> me to think that ye are come to quench the unmer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull heat of a feaver, then only to bedew that which was the ſubject of one. But if it may be, hold a little, and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer your eyes a while to a new employment, even to ſee where you are, what you are doing, whoſe Obſequies you are ſolemnizing with ſo great devotion, and take the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menſions of your loſſe, if it be capable of any: which indeed is ſo great, that they only can know it, who knew not him, and they onely can feel, who never enjoy'd him; I ſpeak not to aggravate your loſs, but the ſenſe of it, as for the cauſe of it, it admits of no addition. Whilſt he lived, it was as impoſsible for him not to love you, as it was for you adequately to return his love: His care an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered his love; and if his ſucceſſe had anſwered his care, we might happily have this day wanted an object of ſo great ſorrow, in enjoying him. His writings were not read without ſatisfaction: His Sermons were ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver heard without an approving ſilence, ſeldom without a following advantage. His kindneſs towards you could not be conſidered without love, his awfull gravity, and ſecretly-commanding preſence, without reverence: Nor his converſation, without imitation. To ſee him live, was a provocation to a godly life; to ſee him dying, might have made any one aweary of living. When God reſtrains him from this place (which was alwayes happy in his company but now) he made his chamber a Church, and his bed a Pulpit, in which (in my hearing) he offered ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny a hearty prayer for you: And his death made him mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of you, whoſe life made you unmindfull of him. And I did not ſee that any thing made him ſo backward to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign up his pure ſoul to God, as his unparalell'd care for you, and your proficiency in godlineſs, which ſeemed as
<pb facs="tcp:119052:17"/> little to him, in compariſon of what he deſired, as it does great to others in compariſon of what they finde; ſo that I ſate by him, and I only, when with as great affluency of Tears, as words, he prayed, Lord (with ſome ingeminati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons) charge not on me the ignorance of this people. And indeed your ignorance had not been ſo remarkable, had not his Knowledge, and deſire ſtill to communicate it been ſo. With what a grace and majeſty have you heard him Preaching, who is now (alas) confin'd to a worſer wood. Could you ever reſiſt the power by which he ſpake; or find in your hearts to contradict any thing that ever he ſaid, but when on his ſick-bed he ſaid, I am a dying man? Ah! who would not there have contradicted him, if they ſhould not have contradicted Gods Decree! His Wiſedome, Juſtice, and Tenderneſs were ſuch predominant Graces in him, that it is as much my inability to deſcribe them, as my unhappineſſe not to im<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tate them: And truly, to think to expreſſe them, were infinitely to in<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ure their greatneſs. It is a ſad thing that ſo many reſplendent graces<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſhould ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be ſo truly, nor ſo fully diſcovered, as by the loſs of him that had them; and that we ſhould not ſo juſtly conſider that he had them, till we have not them. But yet your loſſe might be the better borne, if ye were ſure it had no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of a Judgement in it. But I fear that within a ſhort time, it will appear as truly, that God hath taken him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way in anger, as now it appears ſadly, that he hath taken him away: And that it is not only a miſery that must be repayred by a change of Paſtors, but alſo a ſin which muſt be redreſt by the change of your lives: For, if your un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthineſſe have driven your teacher into a corner, and you ſinn'd him into his grave; your Repentance and Humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation muſt raiſe another out of his aſhes. So great, ſo ſad,
<pb facs="tcp:119052:18"/> ſo generall is this loſſe, that I am ready to excuſe my ſelf, and think it more reaſon then paſſion, if in my ſolitary mournings, and retired complaints, I cry out, My Father, my Father, the horſemen of <hi>England,</hi> and the Charriot thereof. To tell you of his worth in a meaſure proportio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate to my experience, would require too long a diſcourſe from your Infant-Orator. And to tell you of your loſſe, I have ſaid too much already: which although it do not an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer many of your expectations, yet I hope may conduce to the affecting of you to an attention to him, whoſe eloquence can repreſent your loſſe, and whoſe wiſedome can teach you how to make the beſt uſe of it.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>Pag. 1. line <hi>ult. for</hi> And <hi>read</hi> In. p. 2. l. 24. a <hi>Ruler,</hi> r. the <hi>Rule.</hi> p. 5. l. 16. <hi>for</hi> This r. Thus. l. 17. <hi>for</hi> This r. Thus. p. 12. l. 11. <hi>for</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> l 13. <hi>for</hi> Artr. out. p. 20. l. 28. <hi>dele</hi> and wiſe</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
